<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Blog on Walk on the Byte Side</title><link>https://ander94lakx.github.io/tags/blog/</link><description>Recent content in Blog on Walk on the Byte Side</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>ander {at} protonmail {dot} com (Ander Granado)</managingEditor><webMaster>ander {at} protonmail {dot} com (Ander Granado)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Sat, 19 Aug 2023 16:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ander94lakx.github.io/tags/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The blog is now multilingual</title><link>https://ander94lakx.github.io/blog/2023-08-19-blog-multilingual/</link><pubDate>Sat, 19 Aug 2023 16:00:00 +0100</pubDate><author>ander {at} protonmail {dot} com (Ander Granado)</author><guid>https://ander94lakx.github.io/blog/2023-08-19-blog-multilingual/</guid><description>&lt;p>The title says it all, and this post is simply to announce it. From now on, all articles will be available in both English and Spanish.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>That means that, on the one hand, existing articles have been translated into English and, on the other hand, new articles will be published in both languages. My intention is to keep this so that the whole blog is always in both languages.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The default language will be English, but it will always be possible to change it from the new selector that has just appeared at the top. Although English is the default language, if a person comes to the blog, the language will be determined by the language of their browser, so if you access from a browser in Spanish, the content will still appear in Spanish. For the rest of the cases, by default it will be shown in English.&lt;/p></description><content>&lt;p>The title says it all, and this post is simply to announce it. From now on, all articles will be available in both English and Spanish.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>That means that, on the one hand, existing articles have been translated into English and, on the other hand, new articles will be published in both languages. My intention is to keep this so that the whole blog is always in both languages.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The default language will be English, but it will always be possible to change it from the new selector that has just appeared at the top. Although English is the default language, if a person comes to the blog, the language will be determined by the language of their browser, so if you access from a browser in Spanish, the content will still appear in Spanish. For the rest of the cases, by default it will be shown in English.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Although it may seem like more work for a blog with which I am anything but constant, I find it interesting to have it in both languages as it helps me to force myself to write and translate content into English (my mother tongue is Spanish), so it will help me to improve my level. Also, if one day I take this really seriously, having it in English can make the content reach a wider audience.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the future, if I manage to keep it up, I might consider doing something similar (although not completely) with some of the articles, but in Basque, although that&amp;rsquo;s something for the future.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Finally, I apologise in advance if there are typos in English or if my way of writing in English is a bit odd. The content is not translated by professionals but by me (sometimes with tools, let&amp;rsquo;s not pretend we don&amp;rsquo;t), so it won&amp;rsquo;t be perfect (it&amp;rsquo;s not perfect in Spanish, less will be in English XD).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Happy Hacking!&lt;/em>&lt;/p></content></item><item><title>Migrating to Hugo</title><link>https://ander94lakx.github.io/blog/2022-08-14-blog-update-hugo/</link><pubDate>Sun, 14 Aug 2022 14:49:32 +0200</pubDate><author>ander {at} protonmail {dot} com (Ander Granado)</author><guid>https://ander94lakx.github.io/blog/2022-08-14-blog-update-hugo/</guid><description>&lt;p>Hello, aspaldiko! It&amp;rsquo;s been a while since I last posted anything, despite having several ideas in mind and others that I left unfinished (like the series on malware analysis, for example), so it was about time to pick it up again.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>First things first, I think it was time to give the blog a little refresh. A while back, I migrated it from Jekyll to Gatsby to modernize it a bit, but I&amp;rsquo;d been wanting to use something simpler for a while. Not that Gatsby is bad in itself, but it seems to generate too many files for something that should be straightforward, so I looked for alternatives.&lt;/p></description><content>&lt;p>Hello, aspaldiko! It&amp;rsquo;s been a while since I last posted anything, despite having several ideas in mind and others that I left unfinished (like the series on malware analysis, for example), so it was about time to pick it up again.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>First things first, I think it was time to give the blog a little refresh. A while back, I migrated it from Jekyll to Gatsby to modernize it a bit, but I&amp;rsquo;d been wanting to use something simpler for a while. Not that Gatsby is bad in itself, but it seems to generate too many files for something that should be straightforward, so I looked for alternatives.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve known about &lt;a href="https://gohugo.io/">Hugo&lt;/a> for a while, which is advertised as the world&amp;rsquo;s fastest website generator, using Go behind the scenes. Honestly, speed isn&amp;rsquo;t my main concern, but if it generates fewer files and is simpler to use, then it&amp;rsquo;s better. Also, diving into Gatsby without knowing much about React felt a bit daunting.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One of the great things about Hugo is its theme system. You can change themes by cloning repos or adding them as submodules, and it&amp;rsquo;s much easier to handle than in Gatsby. Moreover, the &amp;ldquo;terminal&amp;rdquo; theme I&amp;rsquo;ve chosen looks pretty good, it&amp;rsquo;s minimalist, has that retro touch I like, and still remains modern. If I want to change the look in the future, it&amp;rsquo;s as simple as adding another theme, and that&amp;rsquo;s it. I&amp;rsquo;m not much of a frontend dev, so being able to maintain a good appearance without having to tinker too much is a big advantage.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>On the other hand, another advantage is that you just need to set up your GitHub Action in the repository to build it and push it to the GitHub Pages branch, making it really quick. Just push the changes and forget about it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Still, all of this is just a facelift. The most important thing about a blog is always its content, so this is just a tune-up to get back into blogging, which was long overdue.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the coming days, I&amp;rsquo;ll be uploading a few things to get back into &amp;ldquo;regular&amp;rdquo; posting.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>See you soon!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Happy hacking!&lt;/p></content></item></channel></rss>