<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>presentation on Walk on the Byte Side</title><link>https://ander94lakx.github.io/tags/presentation/</link><description>Recent content in presentation on Walk on the Byte Side</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>ander@protonmail.com (Ander Granado)</managingEditor><webMaster>ander@protonmail.com (Ander Granado)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Sat, 04 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ander94lakx.github.io/tags/presentation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Initial commit</title><link>https://ander94lakx.github.io/blog/2020-04-04-presentation/</link><pubDate>Sat, 04 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>ander@protonmail.com (Ander Granado)</author><guid>https://ander94lakx.github.io/blog/2020-04-04-presentation/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been thinking about creating a blog for years. I don&amp;rsquo;t know if it&amp;rsquo;s because I&amp;rsquo;ve been locked up in my house for 3 weeks (and what&amp;rsquo;s left) due to the quarantine and I&amp;rsquo;m quite bored or if it&amp;rsquo;s just that now I&amp;rsquo;m really ready to get down to it, but even so I&amp;rsquo;ve thrown myself into the adventure.
For those who don&amp;rsquo;t know me, my name is Ander Granado. I&amp;rsquo;m a 25-year-old guy from Vitoria-Gasteiz who studied Computer Engineering and works as a software developer.</description><content>&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve been thinking about creating a blog for years. I don&amp;rsquo;t know if it&amp;rsquo;s because I&amp;rsquo;ve been locked up in my house for 3 weeks (and what&amp;rsquo;s left) due to the quarantine and I&amp;rsquo;m quite bored or if it&amp;rsquo;s just that now I&amp;rsquo;m really ready to get down to it, but even so I&amp;rsquo;ve thrown myself into the adventure.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For those who don&amp;rsquo;t know me, my name is Ander Granado. I&amp;rsquo;m a 25-year-old guy from Vitoria-Gasteiz who studied Computer Engineering and works as a software developer.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As I said, I&amp;rsquo;m a Computer Engineer and, even before I started studying, I like to tinker with different areas within this field. From programming, either web, desktop, mobile, videogames, scripts or tools of any kind, to any other field such as cybersecurity, hacking, the Linux world and anything related to science and technology in general. I&amp;rsquo;m not only a computer programmer, I also like other things like playing videogames, living attached to my headphones and Spotify, travelling, drinking beer or some social or political matters, among others.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There are a lot of topics that I like and that I think it can be interesting to talk about, not because I think my words or opinions are worth reading, but because I think it&amp;rsquo;s an interesting way to generate a kind of personal &amp;ldquo;diary&amp;rdquo;. It can also help me to practice my writing and try writing in other languages, such as English or Basque, so don&amp;rsquo;t panic if you see something poorly written in one of those languages. I also want to underline the word &amp;ldquo;personal&amp;rdquo;. This is completely personal, so anything I put here represents only my point of view.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you are interested in this blog you may find one of the following three things:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>A project abandoned as soon as it starts, by someone who is too lazy to write four fucking lines with any regularity.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A series of disorganised ramblings by a crazed computer engineer.
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Some interesting opinions and articles about programming, hacking, systems, science, technology, music or politics.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>It all depends on how lazy I am over the next few months.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As far as I&amp;rsquo;m concerned, thank you very much for reading me and if you&amp;rsquo;re interested, I have a number of social networks where you can follow me. I have &lt;a href="https://www.instagram.com/andergranado/">Instagram&lt;/a>, where I mainly post pictures of my travels and what I read (very hipster, I know). I also have &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/AnderGrM">Twitter&lt;/a>, which if I haven&amp;rsquo;t abandoned it, is what I use to find out about new things in the development world, follow artists, etc. Finally, although it&amp;rsquo;s not a social network, I have &lt;a href="https://github.com/ander94lakx">GitHub&lt;/a>, where I have uploaded some projects, from old things from university to some little things I&amp;rsquo;m doing (like, for example, this blog).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Ondo ibili!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>P.S.: The blog is made with &lt;del>Jekyll&lt;/del> &lt;del>Gatsby&lt;/del> Hugo, which I think is a great tool to make a blog like this and to host it with GitHub Pages.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>P.S.2: The name of the blog is just a pretty lame fusion of the name of a Lou Reed song with the word byte.&lt;/p></content></item></channel></rss>